Guide to the Frank Ernest Hill Collection, 1905-1969
Department of Special Collections
Frank Ernest Hill Collection,
1905-1969
Special Collections M0212
Hill, Frank Ernest, 1888-1969.
1.5 linear ft.
Stanford University. Libraries. Dept. of Special Collections and University Archives.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
None.
Provenance
Gift of Mrs. Frank Ernest Hill, 1970 and 1971.
Biographical Note
Frank Ernest Hill, son of photographer Andrew Putnam Hill (1853- 1922), born 29 August 1888 in San Jose, California, was a newspaperman, college professor, aviator, poet, and author. He received his A.B. (1911) and A.M. (1914) from Stanford University in English literature. His began his career as a poet, but later turned to expository prose and toward the end of his life wrote industrial history. He died 2 November 1969.
Scope and Content
Collection includes typescripts, with some corrections in pencil ("Geoffrey Chaucer," WINGED HORSE ANTHOLOGY revision, FATHER WAS PRESIDENT, and unpublished poems), correspondence dating chiefly from the 1960's and pertaining to negotiations for the publication of articles and books, and miscellaneous unpublished works by Hill. Also includes biographical material, diplomas, photographs, and illustrations. There is one folder of correspondence from Andrew Putnam Hill and his wife Florence to their son Frank, 1916-1918.
Container List
- Geoffrey Chaucer, unpublished and unused radio script dating from the 1940's (Box 1, Folder 1)
- TLS - Margaret Lesser to FEH, 6/23/47 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- TLS - Margaret Lesser to FEH, 3/29/49
- plus possible additions for new edition (discussed in letters but never published) of Winged Horse Anthology
- TLS - Edward T. James to FEH, 2/27/64 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- T copy FEH to ETJ, 2/10/64
- copy of directions for contributors to Supplement 3 of the Dictionary of American Biography
- T copy, FEH to ETJ, 2/13/64
- T copy, FEH to Owen (Ford Motor Co.), 9/22/64
- TLC, Owen to FEH, 9/25/64
- T copy, FEH to Owen, 9/28/64
- A copy, n.d.FEH to ETJ
- T copy, FEH to ETJ, 10/3/64
- TLS, ETJ to FEH, 10/30/64
- T copy, FEH to ETJ, 11/2/64
- T copy (incomplete) of Edsel Ford article
- T copy of Henry Ford Article with A notes and rough draft
- A notes-outline for Henry Ford Article
- A draft for bibliography
- T copy of 11/64 article version, uncorrected
- T copy, FEH to ETJ, 11/19/64
- TLS, ETJ to FEH, 12/4/64
- T copy, FEH to ETJ, 12/7/64
- These all deal with negotiations for FEH to write the Henry and Edsel Ford articles for the third supplement of the Dictionary of American Biography
- TLS, Harold A. Basilius to FEH, 5/19/64 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- T copy, FEH to David McKay and Co., 5/19/64
- T copy, FEH to HAB. 5/21/64
- TLS, Edward E. Mills to FEH, 5/26/64
- TLS, HAB to FEH, 5/27/64
- T copy, FEH to HAB, 6/2/64
- T copy, FEH to EEM, 6/9/64
- TLS, EEM to FEH, 6/12/64
- T copy, FEH to HAB, 6/16/64
- T copy, FEH to EEM, 6/19/64
- TLS, EEM to FEH, 6/18/64
- T copy, FEH to EEM, 6/22/64
- T copy - introduction to reissue of Chaucer
- TLS, EEM to FEH, 7/1/64
- T copy, FEH to EEM, 7/2/64
- TLS, HAB to FEH, 7/13/64
- T copy of letter and agreement, EEM to FEH, 7/16/64
- T copy, FEH to EEM, 7/28/64
- TLS, EEM to FEH, 7/29/64
- Wayne State University Press Board of Advisors Newsletter, Vol. VIII (1965)No. 1.
- T copy, FEH to HAB, 2/1/65
- TLS, EEM to FEH, 2/7/65
- T copy, FEH to EEM, 2/8/67
- T copy, FEH to EEM, 2/12/67
- TLS, EEM to FEH, 4/4/67
- T copy FEH to EEM, 4/13/67with history of Chaucer translation
- TLS, EEM to FEH, 4/14/67
- T copy, FEH to EEM, 4/15/67
- TLS, EEM to FEH, 4/18/67
- T copy, Mrs. FEH to EEM
- copies of some comments on the Chaucer Translation, copy of review of book in New York Times, 1935
- unpublished poems (1938 - 1969)to his wife, 25 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- copy of TLS, Vincent P. Carosso to Mrs. FEH, 4/2/71 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- A. promotional material and T final draft to introduction of Father Was President by FEH and VPC
- Chap. 1, Father Was President (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Chap. 2, Father Was President (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Chap. 3, Father Was President (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Chap. 4, Father Was President (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Chap. 5, Father Was President (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Chap. 7, Father Was President (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Chap. 8, Father Was President (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Chap. 9, Father Was President (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Chap. 10, Father Was President (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Chap. 11, in note form (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Chap. 11, Father Was President (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Chap. 12, Father Was President (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Chap. 13, Father Was President (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Miscellaneous - list of books on historians (Box 1, Folder 20)
- New York Times obituary
- copy of review of book, What is American? by FEH in New York Herald Tribune, 1933
  1/4/72 ADDITION TO OVERSIZE - ILLUSTRATION FOR CHAUCER'S CANTERBURY TALES, [7th] EDITION, ARTIST
- Correspondence, 1916-1918,mostly from Andrew P. Hill to Florence Hill to Frank and Elsa Hill (Box 1, Folder 21)
- TLS, 5/12/26Stephen T. Mather to Hill with enclosed copy of TL 5/11/26James McCormick to Mather, 1. (Box 2, Folder 1)
  SEE BACK FOR ADDITIONS
- TLS copy, 2/5/62Hill to Manhattan Traffic Court, 2.
- TLS copy, 2/23/62Robert [cocoalt] to Hill re: gift to Columbia University of Letters and correspondence of Sarah Sumner Broughton (1802 - 1853) with copy of perspective on Broughton by Hill., 3.
- TL copy, 4/4/63Hill to Bruce [Bliven], 4.
- TLS, 4/9/63Lawrence H. Chamberlain to Hill, 5.
- TL copy, 4/18/63Hill to Davis F. Pritchett, 6.
- TLS, 5/10/63Allan Nevins to Hill re: who to write comment on Ford Overseas by Hill, 7.
- TLS, 6/25/63Allan Nevins to Hill re: 3rd volume of Ford history, 8.
- TLS, 7/26/63Fred K. Weyerhaeuser to Hill re: Hill's history of Weyerhaeuser Company, 9.
- TPCS, 8/13/63Bruce [Bliven] to Hill, 10.
- TLS, 8/14/63William D. Boutwell to Hill, 11.
- TLS, 12/30/63Earl J. Pallasch to whom this will concern (Hill), 12.
- TLS, 1/7/64Lawrence H. Chamberlain to Hill, 13.
- TL copy, 1/30/64Hill to Ralph [W. Hidy?] re: The New World of Wood and Father Was President, 14.
- TL copy, 2/12/64Hill to Allan [Nevins], 15.
- TLS, 2/13/64Allan Nevins to Hill, 16.
- TLS, 2/14/64Ralph W. Hidy to Hill re: Timber and Men, 17.
- TL copy, 2/17/64Hill to Allan [Nevins] re: work on Father Was President and The New World of Wood, and The Fabulous Forest, 18.
- TL copy, 2/17/64Hill to Ralph [W. Hidy], 19.
- TLS, 3/2/64Allan Nevins to Hill, 20.
- TL copy, 3/5/64[Hill] to Allan[Nevins] re: American Business Abroad, New World of Wood, Father Was President, 21.
- TLS, 4/5/64Allan Nevins to Hill re: proposed book on James Truslow Adams, 22.
- TL copy, 4/7/64Hill to Allan [Nevins], 23.
- TLS, 4/13/64Allan Nevins to Hill re: James Truslow Adams letters, 24.
- TL copy, 4/15/64Hill to Nevins re: J. T. Adams letters, 25.
- TLS, 4/22/64Nevins to Hill re: J. T. Adams letters, 26.
- TL copy, 4/27/64Hill to Nevins re: J. T. Adams letters, 27.
- TLS, 5/4/64Nevins to Hill re: J. T. Adams letters, 28.
- TLS copy, 5/7/64Hill to Nevins re: J. T. Adams letters, 29.
- TLS copy, 5/8/64Hill to Nevins re: J. T. Adams letters, 30.
- TL copy, 5/8/64Hill to Nevins re: J. T. Adams letters, 31.
- TLS, 5/11/64Nevins to Hill re: J. T. Adams Letters, 32.
- TLS, 5/11/64Nevins to Hill, 33.
- TL copy, 5/14/64Hill to Nevins re: J. T. Adams papers and books, 34.
- TLS copy, 5/18/64Hill to Russ[ell Hill], 35.
- TLS copy, 6/2/64Hill to Nevins, 36.
- TL copy, 6/18/64Nevins to Dr. Jacques Barzun (provost of Columbia University, 37.
- TL copy, 6/23/64Hill to Nevins, 38.
- TL copy, 7/11/64Hill to Nevins re: Chaucer and possible teenage book on famous historians., 39.
- TLS. 7/13/64Harold A. Basilius to Hill re: requesting Hill's opinion on Louis Marshall and the Defense of Jewish Rights in the U.S., 40.
- TLS, 7/14/64Stanley Salmen to Hill, 41.
- TL copy, 7/15/64Hill to Stanley Salmen, 42.
- TL copy, 7/29/64Hill to Harold A. Basilius re: Hill's comments on Louis Marshall and the Defense etc., 43.
- TLS, 7/30/64David J. Innis to Hill, 44.
- TLS, 8/6/64Harold A. Basilius to Hill, 45.
- TL copy, 8/17/64Hill to Justin [Miller] re: Chaucer, Famous Historians, relatives, 46.
- 8/27/64ALS [UNK] to [UNK] [UNK], 46.a
- ALS, 8/29/64Justin Miller to Hill, 47.
- TL copy, 8/31/64Hill to Nevins re: Famous Historians, 48.
- TLS, 9/3/64Marilyn Abel to Hill re: submitting American Business Abroad for Pulitzer Prize, 49.
- TL copy, 12/1/64Hill to Allen and Mary Nevins re: Chaucer, Ford, current politics, 50.
- TLS, 12/9/64Nevins to Hill re: references to Masefield, T. S. Eliot, Sandburg, 51.
- TLS copy, 12/15/64Hill to Nevins re: 1 volume Ford history, Famous Historians, 52.
- TLS copy, 12/17/64Hill to Russ[ell Hill], 53.
- TLS copy, 1/24/65Hill to Lyndon Baines Johnson, 54.
- TL copy, 1/26/65Hill to Mary and Allan Nevins, 55.
- TL copy, [1/65?]Hill to Allan and Mary Nevins, 56.
- TL copy, 2/7/65Hill to Allan [Nevins], 57.
- TLS, 2/10/65Douglas Cater to Hill, 58.
- TL copy, 3/31/65Hill to Allan Nevins re: single columer Ford history and Famous Historians, 59.
- TL copy, [5/65?]Hill to Allan and Mary Nevins, 60.
- TL copy, 5/3/65Hill to Russ[ell Hill], 61.
- TL copy, 6/6/65Hill to Anabel, 62.
- TL copy, 6/27/65Hill to Russ[ell Hill], 63.
- ALS, 7/11/65A[llan] N[evins] to Hill, 64.
- TLS, 8/14/65Allan [Nevins] to Frank and Ruth Hill, 65.
- TL copy, 9/2/65Hill to Anabel [Hill], 66.
- TLS, 9/4/65Bruce Bliven to Hill, 67.
- TLS copy, 9/4/65Hill to Editor, The Listener re: politics, 68.
- TLS, 9/9/65Allan Nevins to Hill, 69.
- 9/12/65,TLS copy, Hill to Anabel [Hill], 70.
- TL copy, 11/4/65Hill to Kay and Russ[ell] [Hill], 71.
- TLS copy, 11/12/65Frank Ernest Hill to Frank E. Hill re: package Hill received intended for a different Frank E. Hill of Baltimore, Maryland, 72.
- TLS, 12/6/65Nevins to Hill, 73.
- APS, 1/66Barbara Tuch[man?] to Hill, 74.
- 1/24/66TLS [UNK] to [UNK], 74.a
- TL copy, 1/24/66Hill to Allan and Mary Nevins re: automobile book, 75.
- TLS copy, 2/15/66Hill to Allan Nevins, 76.
- TLS, 2/15/66Seth M. Agnew to Hill, 77.
- TLS, [1966?]Ruth [Hill] to Frank [Hill], 78.
- TLS copy, 2/26/66Hill to Miller, 79.
- TLS, 4/24/66Russell [Hill] to Hill, 80.
- TLS, 4/24/66Allan Nevins to Hill re: Famous Historians, 81.
- TLS, 1/10/67Nevins to Hill, 82.
- TLS, 1/23/67Nevins to Hill, 83.
- TLS, 1/24/67Barbara Kraft to Hill, 84.
- TL copy, 2/26/67Hill to Val May, 85.
- TLS, 3/19/67Russell [Hill] to Ruth and Frank Hill, 86.
- TL copy, 1/67 or 5/67Hill to Allan [Nevins], 87.
- TL copy, 4/14/67Hill to Herbert Baldwin, 88.
- TL copy, 4/24/67Hill to Nevins, 89.
- TL copy, 5/2/67Hill to Russ[ell Hill], 90.
- TLS copy, 8/21/67Hill to William D. Hart re: The Automobile, etc., 91.
- ALS, 1/17/68Mrs. Leland to Hill, 1. (Box 2, Folder 2)
- TL copy, 1/25/68Hill to The Librarian, Library of the Performing Arts, Lincoln Center, N. Y., 2.; (2 copies)
- TL copy, 2/15/68Hill to The Librarian, Library of the Performin Arts, Lincoln Center, N. Y., 3.
- TLS 2/17/68Bernard A Weisberger to Hill, 4.
- TLS. 2/20/68Thor E. Wood (Library of the Performing Arts) to Hill, 5.
- TL copy, 2/24/68Hill to Thor E. Wood re: radio scripts, 6.
- TLS, 3/3/68E. B. Long to Hill re: book on sons of Presidents, 7.
- TLS, 3/5/68Jeanne M. Walsh to Hill, 8.
- TL copy, 3/7/68Hill to E. B. Long, 9.
- TLS 3/29/68Louis [Starr] to Hill with enclosed copy, TLS, Erik Barnouw to Paula Barrett, 10.
- TL copy, 4/8/68Hill to Mary and Allan Nevins, 11.
- TLS, 8/27/68Allan Nevins to Hill, 12.
- TL copy, 9/29/68Hill to Grandson Alan with enclosed 2 copies of 8 page typed essay on Types of Writing and Materials for it - advice and biographical information, 13.
- TL copy, 10/2/68Hill to Russell [Hill], 14.
- TLS, 10/28/68Alan [Hill] to Hill, 15.
- TL copy, [10-11/68?]Hill to grandson Alan: comments on story by Alan, 16.
- TLS, 11/2/68Alan to Hill, 17.
- TLS copy, 11/7/68Hill to Russell [Hill], 18.
- ALS, 11/8/68Alan Hill to Granddad and Aunt Ruth Hill, 19.
- TL copy, 11/16/68Hill to Mary and Allan Nevins re: sons of Presidents book, 20.
- TLS 11/21/68Louis Starr to Hill, 21.
- TL copy, 11/27/68Hill to Louis Starr, 22.
- TL copy, 12/11/68Hill to Alan, 23.
- ALS, [12/68?]Allan [Nevins] to Hill, 24.
- ALS, 12/15/68Mary [Nevins] to Ruth and Frank Hill, 25.
- ALS, 12/25/[68?]Mary [Nevins] to Ruth and Frank Hill, 26.
- TLS, 12/25/68Allan Nevins to Ruth and Frank Hill, 27.
- TL copy, Hill to Harry Emerson Fosdick re: Blacks and education--civil rights, 12/28/68, 28.
- TLS, [12/68]Harry Emerson Fosdick to Hill, 29.
- TLS, 1/5/69Allan Nevins to Frank and Ruth Hill re: The Ordeal, 30.
- TL copy, 1/8/69Hill to Mary and Allen Nevins, 31.
- AL, 3/[8]/69[Allen Nevins] to Frank and Ruth Hill with cover, 32.
- 3/4/69,ALS Alan Hill to Hill, 33.
- TL copy, 3/14/69Hill to Allen [Nevins] re: politics and Father Was President, 34.
- ALS, 3/15/69Robert Duffus to Hill re: ´politics, Jason Goose; on verso, ALS from Leah Louise Duffus to Hill, 35.
- TLS, 3/22/69Russell Hill to Ruth Hill, 36.
- TLS, 3/27/69Andy [Andrew P. Hill - Hill's brother] to Ruth and Frank Hill with enclosed biographical note on Cornelia Barth Hill, deceased wife of Andrew, 37.
- TL copy, 4/5/69Hill to Andy [Andrew P. Hill], 38.
- TL copy, 4/6/69,Hill to Kay and Russell [Hill], 39.
- ALS, [5-8/69?][Birdella Hill?], daughter of Andrew P. Hill to Ruth and Frank Hill, 40.
- TLS, 4/18/69Hill to Leah-Louise and Robert [Duffus], 41.
- TLS, 4/20/69Allan Nevins to Frank and Ruth Hill with postscript by Mary Nevins, 42.
- TLS, 5/21/69Allan Nevins to Hill, 43.
- ALS, [4-5/69]Rachel Hill [granddaughter of F. Hill] to Hill, 44.
- ACS, [6/3/69]Rachel to Hill, 45.
- TLS, 6/4/69Allan Nevins to Hill, 46.
- ALS, [6-7/69]Rachel Hill to Hill, 47.
- TL copy, 7/2/69Hill to Andy [Hill] re: Father Was President, 48.
- TLS, 7/2/69[Mrs. C. Gillard[to Hill, 49.
- ALS, 7/8/69[Harry] A. Hamilton to Hill, 50.
- TL copy, 7/10/69Hill to Victoria L. Schact, 51.
- TLc opy, 7/11/69Hill to Mary and Allan Nevins re: N. Y. politics, 52.
- ALS, 7/14/69Shirley Sargent to Hill, 53.
- ALS, 7/20/69Mary [Nevins] to Ruth and Frank Hill, 54.
- ALS, 7/29/[69]Mary [Nevins] to Ruth and Frank Hill, 55.
- TLS, 8/1/69Allan Nevins to Hill with enclosed copy, TL, 8/1/69Nevins to Warren A. Peters, 56.
- TL copy, 8/1/69Allan Nevins to Charles T. Duncan, 57.
- TL copy, 8/5/69Hill to Allan and Mary Nevins re: Father Was President, 58.
- TLS, 8/5/69Allan Nevins to Hill and William Q. Maxwell, 59.
- ACS, 8/8/69Owen and Georgia [] to Ruth and Frank Hill, 60.
- ALS, 8/19/[69]Mary [Nevins] to Ruth and Frank Hill, 61.
- ALS, 9/2/[69]Mary [Nevins] to Ruth and Frank Hill, 62.
- TLS, 9/3/69Allan Nevins to Hill, 63.
- TL copy, 9/4/69Hill to American Academy of Pplitical and Social Science, 64.
- TLS copy, 9/6/69Hill to Allan Nevins, 65.
- TLS and copy, 9/11/69Hill to Robert Duffus re: politics, 66.
- TLS, 9/24/69Philip Hill [grandson] to Hill, 67.
- TL copy, 9/24/69Hill to Mary and Allan Nevins, 68.
- TLS, 9/25/69Allan Nevins to Hill, 69.
- TLS copy, 9/27/69HILL to Mary and Allan Nevins, 70.
- ALS [9/69]Bridella [] to Ruth and Frank Hill, 71.
- TL copy, 10/2/69Hill to Philip [Hill], 72.
- TLS copy, 10/17/69Gary L. Shumway to Hill with questionnaire on Oral History Projects in U. S., 73.
- TLS copy, 10/20/69Hill to Gary L. Shumway, 74.
- TLS, 10/27/69Allan Nevins to Frank and Ruth Hill, 75.
- TLS, 10/29/69Andy [Hill] to Ruth and Frank Hill, 76.
- ALS, 11/4/69Louis Starr to Ruth Hill - condolences, 77.
- TLS, 11/7/69Henry Ford Jr. to Ruth Hill - condolences with cover, 78.
- ALS, n.d. [7/7/?][Mary Duclous or Mary F. Robinson?] to Hill, 79.
- ALS Xerox, 12/26/60Hill to Mrs. Horace Laughlin (Birdella), 1. (Box 2, Folder 3)
- ALS Xerox, 12/18/63Hill to Birdella, 2.
- ALS Xerox, 1/6/64Hill to Birdella, 3.
- ALS Xerox, 1/8/64Hill to Birdella, 4.
- TLS Xerox with A. diagram and A. postscript, 1/22/64Hill to Birdella, 5.
- ALS Xerox, 9/20/64Hill to Birdella, 6.
- TLS Xerox, 10/11/66Hill to Birdella, 7.
- TLS Xerox, 1/31/67Hill to Birdella, 8.
- TLS Xerox, 2/12/69Hill to Birdella, 9.
- TLS Xerox, 2/12/69Hill to Andrew P. Hill, 10.
- ALS Xerox, 8/29/69Hill to Birdella, 11.
- ALS 10/16/69Hill to Birdella (Xerox), 12.
  These letters deal mostly with Frank Hill's personal life, his work and his daily activities.
- Carbon - jacket notes on Frank Ernest Hill, probably to accompany three volume work on Ford Motor Company, 1. (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Biographical-A Note on My Family and My Own Early Work as a Writer by FEH explanation by [UNK] [UNK] [UNK], 2.
- Notes concerning the five pages entitled Biographical, by Mrs. Horace Laughlin, 3.
- Obituary in New York Times - Frank Ernest Hill, 4.
  See [UNK] [UNK] [UNK]
- Diploma of Graduation - Leland Stanford Junior University, B.A. 5/22/11, 1. (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Diploma of Graduation - Leland Stanford Junior University, M.A. 5/18/14, 2.
- Early Poems - typed and autographed with typed carbon copy (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Poems, 1905 - 1907,autograph manuscript copy with illustrations by Frank Ernest Hill (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Poems, 1908 - 1909with illustrations by Frank Ernest Hill and typed carbon copy (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Debate delivered by Frank Ernest Hill, n.d., 1. (Box 2, Folder 9)
- The Fantasy of the Navigators and the Sea God (2), 2.
- Zoroaster - A Poem, 3.
- Phi Beta Kappa Address - The Saving Fire, a poem by Frank Ernest Hill, 4.
- Go thy way and I go mine... manuscript copy of poem by Frank Ernest Hill, 5.
- The California Redwood Park by Frank Ernest and Florence W. Hill, 6.
- The California Redwood - poem by F. A. Nattinger, 7.
- The Poet Faces the Machine Age, lecture by Frank Ernest Hill, 8.
- The School in the Camps by Frank Ernest Hill, 9.
- Famous Belgians - Guido Gazelle, Poet of Flanders, radio script by Frank Ernest Hill (2), 10.
- Illustrations for Stone Dust (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Miscellaneous post cards, catalogues and newspaper articles not by Frank Ernest Hill, map (Box 3, Folder 11)
- 2 copies, honorable discharge from service (Box 3, Folder 12)
- 2 copies - Army drawing class
- Student [UNK] at the [UNK] (2) 1943-44 - 1945-46, 11 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- [UNK], 12
- [UNK] [UNK] - a [UNK] [UNK] (2), 13